MILAN WIEDEMANN

Wolfson College, Linton Road, OX2 6UD Oxford, UK milan.wiedemann@gmail.com ⋄ www.milanwiedemann.com

PERSONAL SUMMARY

I am a PhD candidate at the University of Oxford investigating processes of change in cognitive therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Testing the theoretical models underpinning cognitive therapy for PTSD has strengthened my understanding of the importance that clinical interventions are rooted in empirical science and continually evaluated and refined through research. I appreciate the importance of innovative research projects testing and evaluating technological advances in health care, particularly in clinical psychology. I value, advocate, and implement open science practices in my work. In addition to my research interests I am enjoying to create open-source software tools that help to visualise and analyse data as well as creative work like filming and editing videos.

EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS

University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

DPhil in Experimental Psychology at the Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Thesis: Processes of Change in Cognitive Therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder Supervised by Prof. Anke Ehlers and Prof. David M. Clark

Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2013 - September 2015

MSc in Psychology

Study focus: Clinical Psychology

Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2011 - September 2013

BSc in Psychology

University of Groningen

September 2010 - August 2011

BSc in Psychology

DRK-Rettungsschule Goslar

July 2008 - March 2009

Rettungssanitäter (in English 'Paramedic')

CLINICAL & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

University of Oxford

 $October\ 2016$ - Present

Part-time Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Creating videos for training clinical psychologists in specialised cognitive behavioural treatments.
- · Teaching and supervising Research Assistants in filming and editing techniques.

University of Oxford

April 2015 - August 2016

Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Production of patient testimonials and educational videos together with clinical psychologists.
- · Animation of psycho-educational illustrations.
- · Administration of text, video and audio content for online therapy programmes.

Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - March 2015

Part-time Research Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

- · Conducting clinical interviews with adolescents for a longitudinal study.
- · Setting up and managing large databases for national and international research teams.

Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow

Intern, Social Psychiatric Department

February 2012 - March 2012 Berlin, GER

- · Conducting initial clinical interviews as well as follow-up interviews under supervision.
- · Making house calls as part of a multidisciplinary team in emergency situations.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Oxford

January 2018 - February 2018

Demonstrator, Department of Experimental Psychology

Oxford, UK

· Module: Psychological Disorders and Individual Differences.

University of Oxford

January 2018 - February 2018

Demonstrator, Department of Experimental Psychology

Oxford, UK

· Module: Psychological Disorders and Individual Differences.

Technische Universität Braunschweig

April 2014 - March 2015

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Practical Course of Psychological Diagnostics.

· Module: Fundamentals of Psychological Diagnostics.

Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - January 2014

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Methodology and Biopsychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Laboratory Experience and Analysis with Statistical Software.

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

University of Oxford

July 2017 - September 2017

Part-time Research Assistant, Faculty of History

Oxford, UK

· Production of promotional video for the workshop: Changing lives: Understanding what enables children growing up in adversity to thrive in modern Britain.

Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

May 2010 - March 2015

Part-time Paramedic

Braunschweig, GER

- · Medical care during the qualified transport of patients.
- · First aid and emergency treatment of patients.
- · Independent ambulance coach driver in the in-house emergency centre.

Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

July 2008 - March 2009

Civilian Service

Braunschweig, GER

- · Getting trained as a 'Paramedic' (in German: Rettungssanitäter).
- · Medical care during the qualified transport of patients.
- \cdot Independent ambulance coach driver in the in-house emergency centre.

SCHOLARSHIPS

Mental Health Research UK

May 2018

Travel Grant

University of Oxford, Wolfson College

June 2017

Travel Grant

Mental Health Research UK

4-year PhD Scholarship

Erasmus plus February 2015

October 2016

March 2019

Graduate Student Scholarship

SELECTED PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience Berlin, 2 days

Preparing for Teaching in Psychology March 2019

University of Oxford, Department of Experimental Psychology, 1 day

Berlin Oxford Teaching Alliance for Quantitative Neuroscience

DeGPT Autumn School October 2018

Deutschsprachige Gesellschaft für Psychotraumatologie, 4 days

Psychological Networks Summer School August 2018

University of Amsterdam, 5 days

Summer School of Advanced Quantitative Methods May 2018

University of Oxford, Department of Education, 5 days

Preparing for Learning and Teaching at Oxford

January 2018

University of Oxford, Medical Sciences Division, 1 day

Testing for Mediation and Moderation Using Mplus

June 2017

Figure It Out - Statistical Consultancy and Training, 1 day

Multilevel Analysis for Longitudinal Data February 2016

Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum, 3 days

Structural Equation Models for Longitudinal Data February 2016

Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum, 2 days

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Statistics & Data science R, Python, Git, JASP, jamovi, Mplus, SPSS

Scientific writing R Markdown, Zotero, LaTeX, BibTeX, Microsoft Office

Video & Audio editing Final Cut X, Audacity, iZotope RX

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed

Kosir, U., **Wiedemann**, M., Wild, J., & Bowes, L. (2019a). Cognitive mechanisms in adolescent and young adult cancer patients and survivors: Feasibility and preliminary insights from the cognitions and affect in cancer resiliency study. *Journal of Adolescent and Young Adult Oncology*. doi:10.1089/jayao.2019.0127

Kosir, U., **Wiedemann**, M., Wild, J., & Bowes, L. (2019b). Psychiatric disorders in adolescent cancer survivors: A systematic review of prevalence and predictors. *Cancer Reports*, e1168. doi:10.1002/cnr2.1168

Wild, J., Warnock-Parkes, E., Grey, N., Stott, R., **Wiedemann**, M., Canvin, L., ... Ehlers, A. (2016). Internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: A development pilot series. *European Journal of Psychotraumatology*, 7(1). doi:10.3402/ejpt.v7.31019

Preprint

Wiedemann, M., Thew, G. R., Stott, R., & Ehlers, A. (2019). suddengains: An R package to identify sudden gains in longitudinal data. *PsyArXiv Preprints*. doi:10.31234/osf.io/2wa84

Software

- Wiedemann, M. (2019a). lcsm: An R package for latent change score modeling. Retrieved from https://milanwiedemann.github.io/lcsm/
- Wiedemann, M. (2019b). shinychange: An interactive tutorial on latent change score modeling in R. Retrieved from https://milanwiedemann.shinyapps.io/shinychange/

PRESENTATIONS

Conference presentations

- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2017). Predictors and processes of sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD. European Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Ljubljana, Slovenia.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2019a). A test of theory-derived mediators of clinical improvement in cognitive therapy for PTSD. World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Berlin, Germany.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2019b). Automating the identification of sudden gains within psychological therapy datasets: A new r package. World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Berlin, Germany.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2019c). Cognitive processes of sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD in routine clinical care. World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Berlin, Germany.

Invited talks

- Wiedemann, M. (2015). Mental health care in England Overview of the improving access to psychological therapies (IAPT) programme. Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow.
- Wiedemann, M. (2016). Digital methods in internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: Results from a pilot study. Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2018a). Processes of change in cognitive therapy for PTSD Sudden symptom improvements during therapy. *University of Groningen, WEIRD Seminar Series*.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2018b). Processes of change in cognitive therapy for PTSD Taking a closer look at how therapy works. *University of Pennsylvania*, *DeRubeis Lab*.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2018c). Sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD
 Can large and stable improvements between sessions help us understand how therapy works?
 University of Exeter, Mood Disorder Centre, The Think-Tank Seminar.